<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from the Commission of the General Assembly of the Church of Scotland to the honourable council and inhabitants of the Scots colony of Caledonia in America dated at Glasgow, July 21, 1699.</title>
            <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly. Commission.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33100</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4231</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R40834</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">19334312</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 19334312</idno>
            <idno type="VID">108656</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A33100)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 108656)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1683:56)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Letter from the Commission of the General Assembly of the Church of Scotland to the honourable council and inhabitants of the Scots colony of Caledonia in America dated at Glasgow, July 21, 1699.</title>
                  <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly. Commission.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert Sanders ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Glasgow :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of Scotland --  History --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Church of Scotland --  Missions --  America.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:108656:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:108656:1"/>
            <p>LETTER FROM THE COMMISSION OF THE General Aſſembly OF THE Church of Scotland TO THE Honourable Council and Inhabitants of the <hi>Scots</hi> Colony of <hi>Caledonia</hi> in <hi>America.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Dated at <hi>Glaſgow, July</hi> 21, 1699.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>GLASGOW,</hi> Printed by <hi>Robert Sanders,</hi> One of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Printers. 1699.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:108656:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:108656:2"/>
            <head>Much Honoured, and dearly belov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, Grace, Mercy and Peace be multiplied unto you.</head>
            <p>THo' in the wiſe and powerful providence of GOD, who <hi>hath determined the times before appointed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 17.26.</note> 
               <hi>and the Bounds of</hi> every man's <hi>Habitation,</hi> you are now ſeparated from us by a vaſt Ocean; yet you are not disjoined from our Hearts; nor ſhall theſe Waters ever quench, nor Time, nor Diſtance wear out our Love to you:<note place="margin">Eph. 1.16.</note> 
               <hi>We ceaſe not to make mention of you in our Prayers</hi> to God for your Preſervation, and for the Proſperity of your Souls; nor to offer Him our humbleſt Adorations, and thankful Praiſes, for the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of His Kindneſs, and Mercy to you (whereof we have received moſt refreſhing Accounts,) and to us in you, whom we juſtly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der as a worthy part of our ſelves, both as we are a Civil and a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Body: and pray we may have reaſon always ſo to do.</p>
            <p>We acknowledge the ſpecial merciful hand of our gracious good God, hitherto moſt ſignally and viſibly appearing in the firſt propoſal, in the Management, and in the Conduct of this Great, and Generous Undertaking, in which you are now ſo far, and happily engaged; That in a poor Nation, altogether unacquainted with the carrying on of ſuch great Deſignes, ſo many Perſons of all Ranks and Qualities ſhould Unite together in ſuch a Contrivance: That they got the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of having a Prince, and Eſtates of Parliament ready to give Life by Law to the ſame: That they who were generally Strangers to Trade, ſhould have been induced to venture ſo conſiderable a Stock, to the ſurprizing of thoſe Abroad, and themſelves at Home; when they could not but lay their Account with many Difficulties, and much Oppoſition: That theſe <hi>noble Patriots</hi> ſhould continue ſo firm, and willing to contribute their ſeveral Proportions of Means, and endeavours to ſet it ſo fairly on Foot, notwithſtanding of ſeveral unforeſeen Diſappointments, and Oppoſitions: That theſe Diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointments
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:108656:3"/> and Oppoſitions, which ſeemed to look towards it with no promiſing aſpect, have fallen out rather unto its furtherance: That a Land known to all the World to be a fit Seat for ſuch an Undertaking, ſhould have lyen hitherto neglected by our more potent Neighbours: That you the firſt <hi>noble Adventurous</hi> have been led out of your Native Country under Divine Direction to this Land, which the Lord had <hi>eſpied</hi> and reſerved for you,<note place="margin">Ezek. 20.6. Exod. 19.4.</note> and to which he hath born you, as <hi>on Eagles wings,</hi> through the Dangers of the great Deep, and as it were aloft over amazing Difficulties, and hath piloted you ſafely in to that Void, but commodious Dwelling, whilſt you mean while, like <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8.</note> (in a manner) <hi>knew not whither you went:</hi> That He hath kept you, in ſo long, doubtful, and hazardous a Voyage: That ſo few, compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratively, have died by the way, or ſince your Arrival; All <hi>this is the doing of the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 118.23.</note> and his marvelous doing, and calls for the humbleſt, and heartieſt Praiſes, and moſt devoted Services from you, and from us.</p>
            <p>We have in part heard of the Providences that have gone over you, ſince your Landing, and have rejoiced to hear of the good hand of our Gracious God continued upon you for Good, in your acceptable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the <hi>Natives:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 24.1. Deut. 32.8. Pſal. 30.9.</note> That He <hi>whoſe the Earth is and the fulneſs thereof,</hi> even <hi>the most High,</hi> who <hi>divided to the Nations their Inheritance, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated the Sons of</hi> Adam, hath made <hi>room</hi> for you with the free con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and good liking of theſe <hi>Natives,</hi> the Natural Lords of the Land; and in the Preſervations you have been under, and the Succeſſes you have obtain'd, whilſt envious Neighbours, who covet more than they are able to poſſeſs,<note place="margin">Iſa. 5.8.</note> 
               <hi>Joining Land to Land, that they may be placed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone in the midſt of the Earth,</hi> are ſeeking to moleſt you, and turn your Poſſeſſions into <hi>Eſek</hi> and <hi>Sitnah:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 26.20.21.</note> That God hath hitherto maintain'd your <hi>Reh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>both,</hi> and, we truſt, ſhall maintain it, and make you fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in the Land.</p>
            <p>Amidſt the refreſhful Relations we had of your happy Succeſſes, it was moſt afflicting to us to hear of the Death of our dear Brethren Mr. <hi>James</hi> and Mr. <hi>Scot</hi> your two Miniſters, whom we ſent alongſt with you, for the Comfort and Edification of your Souls; and we find you have been ſenſibly affected with the ſame: He is the Soveraign Lord who was pleaſed to mingle that bitter Water among your Wine, that, amidſt the many ſignal Smiles of Providence beſtow'd on you, you met with this frowning Cloud, to allay both your, and our Joy; But who may ſay to the Almighty,<note place="margin">Dan. 4.35.</note> 
               <hi>What doſt Thou?</hi> Let us adore the only wiſe God in this Diſpenſation, as calling you to an higher valuing of Goſpel-Ordinances, and, by the want of them, to more enlarged
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:108656:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> deſires after them, and a more diligent Improvement of them when re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored; and as calling us to a more vigorous and tender concern in providing for your Souls Food and ſpiritual Benefit.</p>
            <p>To have and improve the glorious Goſpel in its Miniſtry and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, is the happineſs of a Place and People: Where theſe are, <hi>Glory dwells</hi> in that Land, and without them, there is no Glory:<note place="margin">Pſal 85.9. 1 Sam. 4.21.22.</note> Let Mens Dwellings upon Earth be Fertile and Barren, Wealthy or Poor, Peaceful or Perilous; this compenſats the Inconveniences of the one, and is the richeſt Advantage of the other: How ſweet is the Life, and ſecure is the Protection of theſe who dwel <hi>under the Wings of the God of Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ruth 2.12.</note> and the warm Influences of his Ordinances in their Life and Power!</p>
            <p>The Honourable Court of Directors, by their Applications to the laſt General Aſſembly, and to us, have been careful to repreſent your Deſires to have moe Miniſters ſent you, and very forward in contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buting what was proper for them, to accompliſh the ſame: And we hope we may ſay, it hath been the good Hand of God in anſwering their Endeavours, and ours, that we herewith ſend you Four of our Brethren, Miniſters of the Goſpel of Chriſt, and our Fellow-Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers unto the Kingdom of God; Men who have a great Zeal for you, and have very cheerfully hazarded their Lives, in addicting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves unto this Miniſtry, whom we beſeech you to receive, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit your ſelves unto in the Lord: Tho' we might uſe much boldneſs in Chriſt with you, as our Spiritual Children, in Recommending them as our Brethren; yet it is under an higher and more auguſt Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter they come unto you, and under which you are to receive them, as the Servants of the Living God, as the Embaſſadours of Chriſt, as Men ready to ſpend and be ſpent in the Service of your Faith and Joy, and in communicating this Goſpel to the <hi>Gentiles</hi> in the Regions beyond you:<note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5.12.13.</note> Do you therefore <hi>Esteem them very highly in Love for their Works ſake,</hi> entertain their Meſſage, encourage their Endeavours, and ſtrengthen their Hands: We truſt they ſhall, through Grace, make full Proof of their Miniſtry among you;<note place="margin">2 Cor. 10.6. Heb. 13.17. 1 Theſſ. 2.19.</note> Do you alſo <hi>fulfill your Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to them</hi> in the Lord, as Men that <hi>Watch for your Souls, and must give an Account;</hi> That you may be their <hi>Hope and Joy,</hi> their <hi>Glory</hi> and <hi>Crown of Rejoycing, in the Preſence of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt at his Coming;</hi> and they may Labour amongſt you, and give up their Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of you in that Day <hi>with Joy and not with Grief; for that is unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have fully Inſtructed them to ſet up a Chriſtian Diſcipline, and Order in your Church;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>for God is not the Author of Confuſion but of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:108656:4"/> Order and Peace in all the Churches of the Saints;</hi> and in this they will ſtand in need of ſome of you to be joined with themſelves, as Elders and Office-Bearers in the Church, Overſeers of the Manners of the People, and Aſſiſtants in the Exerciſe of Diſcipline, and Government: And we hope ſuch of you as ſhall be orderly Called hereunto, will reckon it your Duty to embrace the ſame, and diſcharge that Office with Chriſtian Meekneſs, Prudence, and Faithfulneſs: And we are confident of the Zeal and Love of all of you in every thing wherein they may need your Aſſiſtance: Nor will the Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> be wanting in what may be requiſit from time to time, towards the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the Goſpel among you, and diffuſing its Glorious Light and Influence upon the Neighbouring <hi>Gentiles;</hi> that they to whom Chriſt was not <hi>heretofore ſpoken of,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 15.21.</note> 
               <hi>may ſee; and they that have not heard may conſider and underſtand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now <hi>Honoured Friends</hi> and <hi>Dear Country-men,</hi> whilſt you are far from us,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 11.2.</note> our Bowels earn towards you, and we are <hi>Jealous over you with a godly Jealouſie,</hi> leſt any among you forget the Obligations of their Birth, Sacramental Entrance into, and Education in a Chriſtian Church, their Vows in the day of their Diſtreſſes or Fears, the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velous loving Kindneſs of the Lord in your Preſervation hitherto, and Eſtabliſhment; and what Duty and Service theſe wonderful Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences you have met with and ſtill are under do require; leſt there ſhould be any <hi>Achan</hi> in your Camp to trouble your Iſrael, and kindle the Diſpleaſure of your God, provoking Him to turn againſt you to do you Evil, after he hath done you Good. And we hope you will conſider what we ſay as proceeding from the warmeſt Affections of your tender loving Mother <hi>the Church of</hi> Scotland.</p>
            <p>Remember then in the firſt Place, That God is the Soveraign Lord, and abſolute Proprietor of all the Earth; it's He who hath appointed a Place for you, and carried you ſafely to it. He it is, even the Lord of Hoſts, who fights your Battles againſt thoſe who would diſturb your Settlement: From Him you derive your Original Right and your Security; acknowledge Him then as your Great <hi>Land-Lord</hi> with Sincere and Upright Souls: All you enjoy is His, all you expect is from Him; Pay therefore unto Him due Homage for all: Serve Him who is your God, and the God of your Fathers, and the God of this Nation to which you belong; and cleave to Him with upright Hearts; <hi>For the Lord is with you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chron. 15.2.</note> 
               <hi>while ye be with Him; and if ye ſeek Him, He will be ſound of you; but if ye forſake Him, He will forſake you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You are not left like the blind <hi>Heathen</hi> to grope after Him, as in the Dark;<note place="margin">Acts 17.27.</note> He hath been, and Is nigh unto you, and your Eyes have
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:108656:4"/> been opened (even all of you, at leaſt, by Chriſtian Education) to behold him, not only in his wondrous Works, which all Men behold; but in the moſt wonderful of all his Works, in his Glorious Goſpel: By this you have been taught that <hi>God is a Spirit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 4.24. Deut. 12.4, 31.</note> and you muſt <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him in Spirit and in Truth: You ſhall not do ſo unto the Lord your God,</hi> as the <hi>Heathen</hi> do unto their Gods, who ſtupidly, and blockiſhly Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip their blockiſh Idols;<note place="margin">2 Kings 17.26.27.</note> but you muſt remember <hi>the Manner of the God of the Land</hi> from whence you came, and ſerve him after his own Manner revealed in his Goſpel. There you have been inſtructed that in all Places his Eye is upon you, and he obſerves your Hearts and Ways in <hi>Caledonia</hi> no leſs than in <hi>Scotland:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 139.9.</note> 
               <hi>The Wings of the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and the uttermoſt Parts of the Sea</hi> hide not from him: All are his Territories and under his Dominion: 'Tis there you Learn that in <hi>every Nation</hi> and in every Place, <hi>he that feareth God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts. 10.35. 1 Tim. 2.8.</note> 
               <hi>and worketh Righteouſneſs,</hi> that <hi>lifteth up holy Hands without Wrath, or Doubting,</hi> is accepted of him; but that the Workers of Iniquity can no where e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape his Notice, nor get out of the Reach of his Juſtice, but by Fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in to Chriſt, and taking Refuge in that bleſſed Hope which the Goſpel ſets before them.</p>
            <p>We beſeech you to Ponder theſe Things with all due Seriouſneſs; Let them be ever preſent to your Minds, with a Practical Influence, and Operation upon your Spirits, and your whole Deportment; that you Reverence, and Serve, Truſt and Adore, Love and Obey that God whoſe you are, and whoſe are all your Wayes: To him you owe your preſent Settlement, and your future Hopes; See and enjoy his Bounty and Kindneſs in all: Labour to know and diſcern, upon Goſpel-Evidence, that he beſtoweth outward Bleſſings upon you from his Love in Chriſt: This will make <hi>your Caledonia</hi> to be a Land of Promiſe, and a Pledge of that better Inheritance reſerved in Heaven for you, where all the Gold and Riches of the Earth, the Things moſt Valued by Men, heap'd together, do make but a faint Metaphor for the Pavement of that moſt Glorious City: And after all the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitions of this World, what is a Man Profited if he loſe his own Soul?</p>
            <p>Let ſuch as are yet Strangers to Chriſt, repent of all their Sins com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in <hi>Scotland,</hi> or ſince their Arrival in their New Dwellings, and conſider with Aſtoniſhment, with Gratitude, with relenring Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and Shame, how many hundreds of Leagues they have been car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried fafe, through the Vaſt Abyſs, when there was but the thickneſs of a Plank between them and Death, and conſequently between them and Hell; How near they have bordered upon the confines of Eternity;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:108656:5"/> and how dreadful it will be at laſt, if the Waves and Billows of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Wrath ſhall go over their Souls for ever. This is the Doom that every Sinner muſt undergo by himſelf, if it be not taken off by his Surety; and ſuch as Fly not to the Goſpel-Sanctuary, and Refuge, their Sin will ſurely find them out, wherever they go.</p>
            <p>We do moſt earneſtly Intreat and Obteſt you the Honourable and Worthy Perſons in whoſe Hands the Government is Lodged, that you not only be ſhining Paterns your Selves, in all Sobriety, Holineſs and Vertue; But that, with the outmoſt Diligence, and vigilant Care, you procure, that the Deportment and Behaviour of all under your Authority and Influence, be ſuch as becometh the Goſpel; by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding every one to do their Duty, by enacting ſtrick and whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom Laws, and Executing thoſe Laws impartially, and ſpeedily; That no Wickedneſs be Countenanced, or in the leaſt connived at; For why ſhould you bring Wrath upon your ſelves, and the Land, and provoke the holy God to blaſt all your Undertakings? And why ſhould you Forfeit his Bleſſing and Favour promiſed to Righteous Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, and make your Selves Partakers of other Mens Sins? For what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is committed thro' your Forbearance, and Remiſneſs in Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is juſtly Chargable on you: Every Man is Guilty of that Sin which he Reproves not, which he does not Teſtifie againſt, which he can, but neglects to hinder in another; But moſt of all, ſuch as are Rulers of others, and muſt give an Account of them to God, as well as of themſelves.<note place="margin">Lev. 19.17.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt not hate thy Brother in thy Heart, thou ſhalt in any ways rebuke thy Neighbour, and not ſuffer Sin upon him:</hi> And in the Margin it reads, <hi>That thou bear not Sin for him:</hi> This is a Law given unto all; But the peculiar End of Magiſtracy is, to be a Terror unto Evil-doers, and for the Praiſe of them that do Well; To ſet their Eyes of Favour upon the Faithful of the Land; and to cut off all Wicked-doers from the City of the Lord.</p>
            <p>There is yet a ſpecial Obligation upon you, in the Planting and Erecting of a New Colony, to take Care that Religion and Vertue be planted and thrive in it. Owe you not this return to God, who hath brought you thither, and who preſerves and proſpers you? Owe you it not to your Selves, leaſt you Forfeit his merciful Kindneſs, and turn it to bitter Diſpleaſure? Owe you it not to the Nation you are come from; to the Goſpel you have Received, and Profeſt, and to the People you are come among; that they receive not Scandal, and ground of Offence againſt Chriſtianity, from the ungodly Lives of Profeſſed Chriſtians? Have you not Advantages, beyond the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of your Native Land, or any other of a long continuance,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:108656:5"/> where there are ſo many Corruptions, and rooted Habits of Vice, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the people to be eradicated? Your Common-Wealth is in its Infancy; you have in your Hand the firſt Forming of it: your People yet but few, in Compariſon, and their Hearts, we truſt, yet tender, under the ſenſe of Divine Goodneſs, as well as the Apprehenſion of yet impendent Dangers; and ſo more eaſily formed into Obedience and Vertue. Are ye not all perſwaded, that,<note place="margin">Prov. 14.34.</note> as <hi>Righteouſneſs exalteth a Nation, and Sin is the Reproach of any People;</hi> So it muſt be verified in a very ſpecial and eminent Manner upon you, That there is a Juſt and Righteous God, who will call every one to a Reckoning, both for their Perſonal and for their Stational Actions? Are you not Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced that Sobriety, Temperance, Diligence, and all other Moral and Chriſtian Vertues, are truly your Temporal, as well as your Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Intereſt; that your Worldly Affairs cannot thrive without theſe; That theſe are true reaſon of State, by their propitious Influence on Society; and true point of Honour, preventing the Baſeneſs and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famies of Vice, and rendring the Righteous Man more Excellent than his Neighbour, ſolidy Brave, Generous, and Great? Have you not before your Eyes fatal Examples of the ſad Effects of Immorality, and Debauchedneſs in other <hi>Colonies,</hi> ſome of which, inſtead of Propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gating the Goſpel, are become Nurſeries of Scandal to <hi>Infidels;</hi> and have drawn down many formidable Judgements on themſelves? Hath not the Diſſolution of Manners weak'ned, enervated and broken ſome of your Neighbours, and rendred them an eaſie Prey to their Enemies, and the Objects of Divine Vengeance, for their Corruptions, and their Cruelties.</p>
            <p>We beſeech you, for the Lord's Sake, for your own Souls Sake, and for the Sake of your Country, and of your Poſterity, for all that is, and ought to be Sacred, and Dear to Chriſtians, or to Men, that you withſtand, and prevent the corrupting of <hi>your Infant Colony,</hi> that you Oppoſe and Stop the firſt Appearances or Occaſions of Vice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt your People; and keep them cloſe to the ſtrict Rules of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Morality, and a Goſpel adorning Converſation.</p>
            <p>Can any think but the Divine Majeſty will reſent, and Avenge the Helliſh, Unnatural, and Uncreaturly Prophanation of his Dreadful and Holy Name, (a Sin void of Tentation, and full of Horrour) or that ever the <hi>Heathen</hi> will be induced to Adore that God, whom his own Worſhippers Trample upon, and Contemn by prophane Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? And, whereas Oaths, amongſt all Nations, are, and ought to be eſteem'd moſt Sacred, and binding; What Veneration or Credit will they give to the Oaths of thoſe, who Proſtitute them, tho' it were
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:108656:6"/> but in trivial Occurrences of Law, (a ſad abuſe of Judicatories in many Countries, which we wiſh you to avoid) much leſs, when they are made the miſerable Blemiſhes and Stains of common Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>Will not Drankenneſs weaken and brutify your People, and ſpoil all honeſt Commerce, and manly Converſation, and prove an inlet to all Miſchief? A temperat People are Bold and Adventuring, Wiſe and Couragious, and attended with many temporal Bleſſings of an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, proſperous and flouriſhing Condition: while Drunkenneſs beſots, diſpirits, befools, and waſts a Nation. Let this Vice be curbed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you in its firſt beginning: And that vile and wretched Cuſtom deteſted that hath unhappily obtained here, of doing all Buſineſs o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a tippling Bottle.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.19.</note>Let all Uncleanneſs be abhorred: Pollute not <hi>the Temples of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt,</hi> which your Bodies are, Conſecrated to him in Chriſtian Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm;<note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 4.4.</note> but let every one <hi>poſſeſs his Veſſel in Sanctification and Honour;</hi> leſt the Place of your Settlement be defiled, and the Land Spue you out, as <hi>Canaan</hi> did its Inhabitants. And let Intereſt oblige you to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Caution, and Watchfulneſs over the People, with reſpect to the <hi>Nat ves,</hi> in this Matter; leſt their Reſentment prove a Mean of your Ruine; and, if they ſhould be provoked to avenge Indignities done them, and Injuries of this kind, your fall could not but prove Diſgraceful and Unpitied.</p>
            <p>Let your Laws ſtrike ſeverely againſt Idleneſs, and want of Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the Parent of much Miſchief and Beggary. Idle People are not only Uſeleſs, but Burdenſom in a Common-wealth, Sowers of Sedition, Diſcontented, and ſeldom better exerciſed, than to find out baſe and diſhoneſt Ways, whereby they may be maintain'd, in pampering of ſloathful Luſts. Let Induſtry be reputed Honourable, and Diligence in Imployment a Character of Vertue, worthy of the higheſt Reſpect: Let not the fooliſh Notion ever get Footing with you, which hath been one great Cauſe of the Poverty of our Nation at Home, and our Reproach among the Rich, and Trading Nations Abroad, That it is below a Gentleman to follow Trade and Imployment.</p>
            <p>Let not only all Falſhood in Words and Actions be ſeverely puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as what is inconſiſtent with Humane Society, and Enervats and Deſtroys Trade; (Faith, and uprightneſs in Dealing, being the Life and Soul of Commerce,<note place="margin">Prov. 10.9.</note> and the beſt Foundation of Succeſs, <hi>for he that walketh uprightly walketh ſurely</hi>) But likewiſe Diſcourage and Diſgrace Self-ſeeking, and Narrowneſs, to the prejudice of the Publick: Let not every one ſeek his own Things, to the Detriment of his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, but every one the Good of others, and common Benefit; for
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:108656:6"/> in the Intereſt of the Publick, and Proſperity of the Common-wealth, that of each particular Perſon conſiſts, and is beſt ſecured. Eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally this is to be look'd to, in the beginning of a Settlement, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy of a Government; where Publick Spiritedneſs and Self-denial, as they are Goſpel-precepts, ſo, will be found beſt Principles of Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; whereas Self-ſeeking hath ever been the Bane and Ruine of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny promiſing Undertakings.</p>
            <p>We cannot forget to Recommend to you Brotherly-Love and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, and that you Live in Peace and Unity among your Selves; a Thing no leſs Profitable to you, than Pleaſant to the God of Peace, and ſuitable to the Chriſtian Name: This is our Lord's New Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment left by Him in Legacy to all his Followers,<note place="margin">Joh. 13.34, 35.</note> that they <hi>Love one another:</hi> By this ev'n the <hi>Heathen</hi>-Nations ſhall know that you are the Diſciples of the Prince of Peace. We need not tell you what is the Common-remark on theſe of our Nation, that, however Haſty, Impatient, and Warm they may be in their Debates, while at Home; yet they are Noted as Exemplary to others, in an affectionat Concern in, Sympathy with, and cloſe Adherence to one another, when Abroad. We heartily Wiſh this may be Verified of you, now when you are far removed from your Native Land, and plac'd amidſt envious Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, who are waiting for your Halting, and would make it their Work to Improve, to your Hurt, any Difference that might ariſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you.</p>
            <p>Let righteous Judgement be Executed betwixt Man and Man; for the Judgement is the Lords. Let it be done Impartially, without vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Quibbles or dilatory Forms, and Diſpenſed either <hi>Gratis,</hi> or u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon a publick Salary; ſo as no Magiſtrat may Gain by Fynes of his own Impoſing; a Practice moſt hurtful in your Native Land; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Covetous are Tempted to Squeeze and Oppreſs, and thoſe of a more honeſt and free Diſpoſition, to become over Slack, left they ſhould appear gripping for their own Intereſt. And in general, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever <hi>Scripture</hi> or <hi>ſolid Reaſon</hi> hath Diſcovered to you to be Wrong, or of ill Conſequence, in the Cuſtoms you have ſeen at Home or elſe where, and in the Errors of other Plantations, let theſe Things be carefully Avoided in your New Government.</p>
            <p>The Eyes of God, of Angels and of Men are upon you; The World begins to take Notice of you, as a moſt hopeful <hi>Colony,</hi> to the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy of your Enemies, and the Joy of your own Country and Friends. Remember, as you are a People of great Expectation, and of great Advantages; So your Honour and Renown, your Temporal, as well as your Spiritual and Eternal Gain ſhall be Great, if you improve your
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:108656:7"/> Talent, and Manage the Price put in your Hands, Wiſely and Well; but if otherwiſe, your Reckoning muſt be Sore and Heavy, and your End Inglorious.</p>
            <p>We again Repeat our moſt earneſt Intreaties unto you, our Dear and Honoured Friends, that you be very Exact, Vigilant, and Conſcientious in Modeling your New <hi>Colony</hi> to all Vertue, and Godlineſs; Eſpecially in the firſt Beginning; which is of vaſt Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance in all great Undertakings; And a due Care of which will render all after Proceedings Eaſſe, Pleaſant, and Succesful; That you bend your outmoſt Endeavours, both by Example and Law, to make Righteouſneſs, Sobriety, and Godlineſs appear in the Eyes of others, as they are in themſelves, Amiable and Honourable; And all Vice and Impiety, Deteſtable and Infamous; So as a vitious Perſon may look like a Monſter, and Object of Horrour amongſt you: Thus, Religion and Vertue will Incorporat into your very Cuſtoms and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, and your Laws and Perſons will be Venerable, without the grievous Neceſſity of being Severe; and God will Bleſs you, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to Dwell among you;<note place="margin">Iſa. 62.4. Ezek. 43.</note> and your Land <hi>ſhall be called Hephzi-bah,</hi> and the Name of your Place <hi>Jehovah-ſhammah, the Lord is there.</hi> But if any will do Wickedly, if Men will be Fooliſh and Froward, your Duty to God, and Mercy to the Community, calls for Speedy and Exemplary Juſtice, that you may put the Evil away from among you, and that Others may Hear and Fear.</p>
            <p>As we Recommend unto you a Juſt and Chriſtian Regard to all Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel-Ordinances; So in Particular, a Religious Obſervance and Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the Lord's Day, the Neglect of which will ly heavy on Governours, the Command being peculiarly giv'n to them, as Perſons that muſt Anſwer for their Children and Servants, and for the Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that is within their Gates, as well as for Themſelves: If the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath of the Lord be Prophan'd,<note place="margin">Lev. 26.43.</note> He will cauſe your Land <hi>to Enjoy its Sabbaths,</hi> by Deſolation. But if you Sanctifie the Holy Day of Reſt unto the Lord, he will Procure and Maintain Reſt for you in your Land.</p>
            <p>And as we are hopeful of your Juſt and Faithful Dealings with all Men, whom you may have Occaſion to Negotiat, and Trade with; So we Recommend, not only Equity and Juſtice, but, obliging Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs towards the <hi>Natives;</hi> That your People may not only have their Converſation Honeſt among the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> but winning and engaging, by Beneficence; That they, Beholding and Enjoying the Benefit of your Good-Works, may Glorifie God in the Day of your Viſitation. If you Partake of their Temporal Things, are you not bound to Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter unto Them of your Spiritual Things? Verily, their Debtors you
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:108656:7"/> are; And not only is it the Intereſt of your Trade, and your Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to keep good Meaſures with them; but 'tis your poſitive Duty, for which the Lord ſeems in a peculiar Manner to have Deſigned <hi>your Plantation,</hi> as its moſt glorious End; To Propagat the Light of his Goſpel amongſt them, and that Heavenly Wiſdom which is more Precious than all Riches, and whoſe Merchandiſe is better than the Gold of <hi>Ophir</hi> or <hi>Darien:</hi> 'Tis by their Conſent that God Confirms your Right, therefore Cheriſh them, as your Brethren, of the ſame Blood, and Kindred in <hi>Adam;</hi> And Endeavour that you may have them alſo your Brethren in Chriſt; not only, let no Stumbling-block, or Occaſion of Offence, be laid before them, but all due Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment giv'n them, to Embrace the Everlaſting Goſpel. Let them ſee what Veneration, and Regard you Pay to your Miniſters, as the Servants of the moſt High God, who muſt Labour amongſt them; and to the Ordinances of Jeſus Chriſt, as the Common Means of your and their Salvation.</p>
            <p>It will be needful you Study their Genius Well: For ſome of theſe Nations are Naturally more Sincere, and Simple; Others more Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile, and Treacherous; But, Generally, all of them, Eſpecially in the Beginning, Suſpicious and Jealous, Credulous, and Apt to take Ill Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, and not Eaſie to Quit them; Alſo moſt Revengful, and Cruel, where they can be Maſters, upon the Apprehenſion of the leaſt Injury done them, to which they have got too many Irritations, by other <hi>Europeans,</hi> who have come among them. Therefore, there's need, you be, in the midſt of them, Wiſe as Serpents, and Harmleſs as Doves: You are always to be very Watchful, and upon your Guard, that you may prevent Surprizals, and be able to Defend your Selves, if they ſhould take up any Prejudice, and Irritation, Groundleſly, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you: Be very Concerned to See that none of Yours Injure, or Diſoblige Them in the leaſt, without Due and Speedy Puniſhment, and that more ſeverely Inflicted, than for theſe Injuries done by any of you againſt another of your Selves. And, beſide the Puniſhment you may find Juſt, and Neceſſar to Inflict, be ſure any Dammage they Suſtain be Repay'd, tho' it ſhould be done by the Publick, when the Offending-Party is not able. By any Means, by continual Converſe, endeavour to Civilize them, and cultivat any Principles of Natural Underſtanding, and Reaſon, they have, which will indeed require great Prudence, and Dexterity in the Manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: And when they ſee Piety, Sincerity and Equity Flouriſhing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong You; it will be the moſt Effectual, and endearing Tye to Knit them to your Intereſt.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:108656:8"/>
            <p>Be careful in doing Juſtice betwixt Maſters and Servants: Let their Service be a reaſonable Service, and Time allow'd them for their Publick and Privat Worſhipping of God, for they are your Brethren: And when their Time Expires; let them meet with ſuch Encouragement, as may always Engage them to continue, and Settle among you: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, from time to time, you will be Strength'ned, and Increaſed, and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Encouraged to come unto You.</p>
            <p>If You ſhall have Servants for Life, or Slaves, of other Nations; (for the <hi>Natives</hi> of <hi>Darien,</hi> we conſider as your Confederats and <hi>Allies</hi>) as we Wiſh you to be Tender, both of their Souls and Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and to Encourage their Converſion to <hi>Christianity,</hi> by all proper Means; So we do not Urge that their abſolute Liberty, and Freedom from their Service, ſhould, as in ſome other Places, be made the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediat Reward of their Profeſſing to Receive the Goſpel: For this hath tempted Maſters to withhold them from the Means of their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, leſt they ſhould be Indammaged by the Loſe of their Service; and hath occaſion'd the Slaves to make Counterfeit Profeſſions, to gain their Liberty. But we Recommend a Gentle-Rule, a Mild Treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that full Acceſs and Time be Allow'd for their Chriſtian Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and let ſuch Rules be agreed on, as that theſe at leaſt of them, who ſhal, not only Profeſs the <hi>Chriſtian-Religion,</hi> but have ſuch a Goſpel-Adorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Converſation, as may Recommend them to the Conſciences of the Godly, as Chriſtians indeed, may have their full Freedom by ſuch Means, and upon ſuch Terms, as may be Safe and Advantagious, both to their Maſters and Them. Immortal Souls are of great Value, and the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of Theſe, who are ready to Periſh, are not to be Deſpiſed.</p>
            <p>We ſhall, in the next Place, particularly Addreſs our Selves to You, that are in Military-Charge, and have Command over the Souldiery, whether by Land or Sea: It's on you, <hi>Honoured and Worthy Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> that a great Share of the Burden of the Publick Safety lyes; you are, in ſome Reſpect, both the Eyes, and Hands of this Infant <hi>Colony:</hi> Many of you have been lately Engaged in a Juſt and Glorious War, for Retriving, and Defending the <hi>Proteſtant-Religion,</hi> the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and Rights of your Country, under the Conduct of a <hi>Matchleſs Prince,</hi> And now, when thro' the Bleſſing of the Lord of <hi>Hoſts,</hi> His and Your Arms have procured an Honourable Peace at Home; You, and others with you, have, with much Bravery, embark'd your Selves in a Great, Generous, and Juſt Undertaking, in the Remote Parts of the Earth, for Advancing the Honour and Intereſt of your Native-Country: If in this you acquit your Selves like Men, and <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> Your Fame will be Renown'd both Abroad and at Home. We cannot Foreſee what
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:108656:8"/> Oppoſition you may meet with from the Malice of Men, who Envy the Proſperity of Others, and ſeek to Enhance to Themſelves that Part of the World whether you are Going, which may juſtly Oblige you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new to the Trial of your Arms: And in that Caſe, you are Called to Uſe your Valour, and Courage, but not to Lean unto it, nor Truſt in the Arm of Fleſh. Seek to have <hi>the Lord Going before you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 52.12.</note> 
               <hi>and the God of</hi> Iſrael <hi>to be your Reerward.</hi> And Remember what is giv'n in Charge to the Armies of <hi>Iſrael, when the Hoſt goeth forth against thine Enemies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 23.9, 14.</note> 
               <hi>then keep Thee from every wicked Thing,</hi> leſt the Lord, ſeeing Wickedneſs, and Prophanity in your Camp, be provok'd to Turn away from you. How Reproachful would it Prove to the Profeſſion of <hi>Christianity,</hi> if, by the lewd Practice of any among you, the <hi>Pagan</hi>-Nations ſhould have Ground to Apprehend, that you Entertain that Helliſh, and falſe Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ime of the Atheiſtical Debauchees of this Age, which ev'n the Refined <hi>Heathen</hi> Abhor, That 'tis a Point of Gallantry, and a neceſſary Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication in a Souldier, to caſt off all Thoughts of God, of his own Soul, of Heaven, and Hell; As if Theſe, who are continually Converſant in the Jaws of Death, were leſs Concerned, than Others, to Mind their Future State; or that Wicked, and Profligat Men, could Adventure to Encounter with Death, which to Them is a King of Terrors, with that Boldneſs and fixed Reſolution, in Lawful and Allowable War, that is to be found with the Upright Man, who can encourage Himſelf with the Thoughts of This, That his Latter-end will be Peace? Do not <hi>Pagan,</hi> as well as <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> Hiſtories, furniſh ſufficient Inſtances of the Nobleſt <hi>Hero's,</hi> and braveſt Commanders, who were Themſelves Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terns of Vertue, and a Terror to the Vitious, and Prophane? And, ſure, the moſt Eminent of Saints, Recorded in the Holy Scriptures, have been moſt Couragious Warriours, and the Beſt of Souldiers. Let Us therefore earneſtly Intreat, and Obteſt You, who are Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Officers, to go before your Souldiers, in all Manner of Holy Converſation. The Characters you bear, by the Stations you are plac'd in, the Reſpect you owe to the Honour, Credit, and Welfare of your Native Country, and that New Part of it, the <hi>Colony</hi> you are now Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to, your own Temporal, as well as Spiritual, Intereſt, and the Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of Theſe under your Charge, do all call aloud on you, to Uſe your outmoſt Endeavours, for Curbing, by Exemplary Puniſhment, and Marks of Diſgrace, in any of your Souldiers, who may be Guilty of them, the Horrid Wickedneſs of prophane Swearing, Unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Drunkenneſs, Prophaning the Lord's Day, Neglect of Goſpel-Ordinances, Falſhood, Treachery, Oppreſſion, and Idleneſs the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of All Wickedneſs, and other Enormities; the Suppreſſing of all
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:108656:9"/> Which we have already Recommended to the <hi>Honourable-Council</hi> of the <hi>Colony:</hi> nor ſhall we need to Enforce this on you, ſo far as your Stations call for it, with any other Arguments than what We have Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to Them, Which we Intreat you Seriouſly to Mind. And, for the Encouragement of all under your Command to Carry, as becometh Chriſtian-Souldiers, in the Way of Well-doing; Let their due Allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance be Punctually giv'n Them; Preferment, and Reward, Imparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, and Readily Beſtow'd on the beſt Deſerving of Them: That Wickedneſs being Diſgrac'd, and Baniſhed; Piety Encouraged and Flouriſhing in your Camp; you may have Confidence toward God, that the Lord will be your Protection, and will Delight to go Forth in the Midſt of You.</p>
            <p>Tho' much of what We have Written be Addreſs'd, Principally, to the Governours and Magiſtrats of the <hi>Plantation,</hi> and Others bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Office among you; Yet it doth likeways Concern every one of You, <hi>Our Beloved Friends, and Dear Country-men,</hi> for whom the Deſire of our Souls, and Prayer to God is, that you may be Saved, that God may Countenance, and Bleſs your Undertakings, and Crown Them with Succeſs, that His Almighty Power may be a Wall of Fire about You; But, above all, that his Gracious Preſence, in his Ordinances, may be the Glory in the midſt of you; and that your Souls may Proſper un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till you be Transplanted into the better Manſions above, that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom which is beyond the Injuries of envious Enemies, a Kingdom that cannot be Shaken, and whence you ſhall go forth no more.</p>
            <p>We have found it Neceſſary, from a ſenſe of our Duty before God, and our tender Regard, both to your Souls, and your outward Well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, to lay before your Governours the indiſpenſible Obligations of their Station, as Chriſtian-Magiſtrats, to Set up, and Maintain a Holy, Righteous-Government over you, and to Suppreſs, and Puniſh all Vice, with the Greateſt, and moſt Impartial Severity. As this is abſolutly Requiſit to the very Civil Subſiſtance of your <hi>Colony,</hi> ſo we hope it will not be grievous to any of you, and that there is not one Soul ſo Degenerous, and Diſſolute in your Society, as, but to Wiſh for a Connivance to any Immoral or Prophane Practice: And, if there be, ſuch a Perſon is a Burden and Plague to the Reſt, that deſerves to be cut off, leſt the Body be Infected, and the heavy Judgements of God be pull'd down on the Community. We are, therefore, Confident that you will Obey, not only for Fear, but, for Conſcience Sake, and for your own Intereſt; That you will Pay all Submiſſion and dutiful Deference to your Rulers; That you will, with Patience, and Content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, bear the Toils and Fatigues of your firſt Settlement, not Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:108656:9"/> for what Uneaſineſs may as yet be in your Circumſtances; but Waiting upon the Land, in an Humble, and diligent Application to your preſent Work, till He in his infinit Mercy, give you a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed Reſt in the Land: For, tho' you do not find ſuch Fruits at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending your preſent Labours, as may Anſwer all the Expectations you had; Yet Patience, Diligence, and Induſtry will overcome your firſt Difficulties; And, thro' the Bleſſing of God, you ſhall find the Promiſe made out unto you, That <hi>the Hand of the Diligent maketh Rich.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And we Ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt you, by the Mercies of God, in Jeſus Chriſt our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, that in your ſeveral Stations, you Walk Worthy of the Lord, unto all Well-pleaſing; That you give no Offence to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> but be exceeding Wary and Tender of whatever may Scar them, from <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity,</hi> or doing any thing Unbecoming the Church, and Members of Chriſt; <hi>That you be Blameleſs and Harmleſs, the Sons of God, without Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke,</hi> ſhining as Lights in the World; That you be Diligent and Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, Sober and Loving, among your Selves; and Obſequious to them that are Over you, whether in Matters Religious or Civil; And that you be every one Exemplary, Encouraging, and Edifying to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in Godlineſs, and in whatever tends to Common-good.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Finally Brethren, whatſoever things are True, whatſoever things are Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, whatſoever things are Juſt, whatſoever things are Pure, whatſoever things are Lovely, whatſoever things are of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ood Report, if there be any Vertue, and if there be any Praiſe, think on theſe Things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And, Particularly, we Recommend unto you, Frequency and Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vency in Prayer, both a-part, and in Chriſtian-Societies, or Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips together. <hi>'Tis God moſt High, who Performeth all Things for You,</hi> on Whom you muſt Depend, for all your Mercies, and all your Hopes: And therefore, <hi>from the uttermoſt Ends of the Earth, lift up your Cry un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Him,</hi> who is the Hearer of Prayer: and you ſhall not ſeek his Face in Vain.</p>
            <p>That we be not further Tedious to you, hoping our Dear Brethren the Miniſters, we have ſent to Labour among you, in the Work of the Lord, ſhall be Furniſhed by Their Great Maſter, ſo as to afford you from his Holy Word, ſuch Inſtructions and Directions, from time to time, as your Caſe ſhal require, to whom we intreat you to Hearken; that you may be mutually encouraging to one another in the Lord your God: We only Repeat theſe Memorable Words, which we Wiſh may be indelibly Engraven on your Hearts: <hi>The Lord is with you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chron. 15.2.</note> 
               <hi>while you are with him; and if you ſeek him, he will be found of you: but if you forſake him, he will forſake you;</hi> And all your forward Expectations, and blooming Hopes ſhall be Blaſted and Wither, and your <hi>Colony</hi> laid
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:108656:10"/> Deſolate, your Names, inſtead of Honour and Renown, ſhal be Branded with Infamy, Hiſſing and Scorn; and your Bleſſings turn'd unto Curſes; and the Lord ſhall Pluck you up,<note place="margin">Deut. 29.21.</note> and not Plant you, <hi>and ſhall ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate you unto Evil,</hi> after he had ſaid, he would do you Good.</p>
            <p>But, <hi>Beloved Brethren,</hi> we are perſwaded better things of you, and things that accompany Salvation, tho', for your Warning, we thus Write; and that the Lord will preſerve you ſtedfaſt in Holineſs, and Faith; and will Plant you in that Place deſtinated for you, and make you a Name of Joy, and Renown among the Nations.</p>
            <p>Now, to Conclude, we Recommend theſe few Words of Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, proceeding from a moſt Tender, and affectionat Concern, for your Good, to your moſt ſerious Conſideration, and to the Bleſſing of God. To him we Commend all of you, and to the Word of his Grace, which is able to Build you up, and to give you an Inh ritance among them that are Sanctified, thro' Faith that is in Chriſt; <hi>To whom be Glory, For Ever and Ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:108656:10"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
